Finding Aid for Cathedral Church of St. Paul (Detroit, Mich.) Records, 1824-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Cathedral Church of St. Paul (Detroit, Mich.) Records 1824-2002
Cathedral Church of St. Paul (Detroit, Mich.)
89503 Ba 2 BA oversize
The Cathedral Church of St. Paul was founded in Detroit in 1824 as St. Paul⿿s parish. The record group spans the period from 1824 to 1995 and includes church registers of services, meeting minutes, and other documentation of the administrative life of the church. The record groups also includes record books of baptisms, marriages, and burials from 1824 to 1936.
25 linear feet
19 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was deposited by Cathedral Church of St. Paul (donor no. 9205 ) on January 30, 2006.
The record group is open to research.
St. Paul's parish was founded in 1824 in what was then the Territory of Michigan. Services were originally held in the Indian Council House on the corner of Jefferson Avenue and Randolph Street. The first church building, consecrated in 1828, was on Woodward Avenue, in the block of Congress and Larned. The church moved in 1851 to the corner of Congress at Shelby, just west of downtown.
The Cathedral Church of St. Paul at the corner of Woodward and Hancock was designed by Ralph Adams Cram (1863-1942) and construction began in 1908 and was completed in 1911. He chose to design the Cathedral in the 14th century English Style of Gothic architecture. The massive pillars which support the roof are more typical of Norman architecture, which preceded Gothic. The Cathedral is build according to medieval construction techniques with no steel superstructure. The Cathedral Church of St. Paul is an important landmark in Detroit and exemplary of the city's exceptional architectural heritage.
As the oldest Episcopal church in Michigan, St. Paul's has been instrumental both in the establishment of other Episcopal parishes, but also in the formation of the Diocese of Michigan, organized in 1832. Long before its official designation in 1906, St. Paul's has served as the "Cathedral Church." In 1958, the church changed its name from St. Paul's Cathedral to the Cathedral Church of St. Paul.
The Cathedral Church of St. Paul records span the period from 1824 to 1995 and includes church registers of services, meeting minutes, and other documentation of the administrative life of the church. The record groups also includes record books of baptisms, marriages, and burials from 1824 to 1936.
The record group consists of seven series: Church Registers; Administrative Records; Church Publications, Annual Reports/Annual Meeting Reports, Vestry Records, Topical Files, and Miscellaneous earlier records.
Subjects:
Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Detroit.; Cathedral Church of St. Paul (Detroit, Mich.); Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Detroit.
- Church Registers 1824-July 1995
  The Church Registers series (approx. 3.0 linear feet and 14 oversize volumes) dates from 1824 to July 1995 documents church attendance and membership. It is divided into three subseries: Attendance Records (June 1924-July 1995); Baptisms; Marriages, Confirmations, and Burials (1824 to 1936), and Membership Lists/Family Records (1936-1940).
  - Attendance Records June 1924-July 1995
    - June 1924-December 1941 (Box 1)
    - January 1942-December 1953 (Box 1)
    - December 1953-May 1955 (Box 1)
    - May 1955-January 1958 (Box 1)
    - January 1958-September 1960 (Box 1)
    - September 1960-March 1963 (Box 1)
    - March 1963-September 1965 (Box 1)
    - September 1965-August 1967 (Box 1)
    - August 1967-April 1969 (Box 1)
    - April 1969-November 1970 (Box 1)
    - November 1970-May 1972 (Box 1)
    - May 1972-November 1973 (Box 1)
    - November 1973-June 1975 (Box 1)
    - June 1975-April 1978 (Box 2)
    - April 1978-January 1981 (Box 2)
    - January 1981-October 1985 (Box 2)
    - December 1985-September 1989 (Box 2)
    - September 1989-November 1992 (Box 2)
    - November 1992-July 1995 (Box 2)
  - Baptisms, Marriages, Confirmations, and Burials 1824-1936
    - 1824-1904 (Box 3)
    - 1863-1867 (Box 3)
    - 1867-1908 (Volume 12)
    - 1906-1910 (Volume 13)
    - 1906-1936
      - Index (Volume 14)
      - Baptisms (Volume 15)
      - Marriages (Volume 16)
      - Burials (Volume 17)
      - Communicants (Volume 18)
      - Confirmations (Volume 19)
    - 1824-1904 (Volume 11)
  - Membership Lists/Family Records 1936-1940
    Membership Lists and Family Records is a series of five oversized volumes that largely overlap in alphabetical jurisdiction and dates covered.
    - A-K (Volume 6)
    - A-K (Volume 7)
    - S-Z (Volume 8)
    - A-Z (Volume 9)
    - L-R (Volume 10)
- Administrative Records 1824-1989
  The Administrative Records series (approx. 4 linear feet and 1 oversize volume) spans the dates 1824-1989, and documents the administrative functions of the church. It is divided into two subseries: Meeting Minutes and Financial Records. Meeting Minutes (1824-1989) documents church-wide meetings, including the Altar Guild, and includes founding documentation and the church's original constitution. Financial Records (1825-1929) documents pledges, donations, offerings and the day-to-day accounting of the cathedral.
  - Meeting Minutes 1824-1989
    - General 1824-1941
      - 1824-1967 (Box 4)
      - 1867-1901 (Box 4)
      - December 1901-April 1914 (Box 4)
      - April 1914-April 1923 (Box 5)
      - April 1923-May 1929 (Box 5)
      - May 1929-May 1935 (Box 5)
      - May 1936-1941 (Box 5)
    - Altar Guild December 1949-1989, 15 folders
      - December 1949-December 1954, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - January 1955-November 1958, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - December 1958-December 1962, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - January 1963-June 1966, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - December 1966-December 1970 (Box 6)
      - January 1971-December 1976 (Box 6)
      - January 1977-December 1984 (Box 6)
      - January 1985-December 1985 (includes Treasurer's Reports, 1979) (Box 6)
      - January 1986-December 1986 (Box 6)
      - January 1987-December 1989 (includes Membership Lists and Memorial Funds Registry) (Box 6)
      - Evening Guild 1960-1967 (Box 6)
  - Financial Records 1825-1929
    - 1825-1872 (Box 7)
    - 1901-1910 (Box 7)
    - 1917-1918 (Box 7)
    - 1918-1919 (Box 7)
    - Pew Pledges 1906-1910 (Box 7)
    - Collections 1854-1855, 2 volumes (Box 7)
    - Subscriptions 1885, 1927-1929, 2 volumes (Box 7)
    - Ladies Sewing Circle 1836-1842 (Box 7)
    - Contributors to the Building Fund (Box 7)
    - Contingent Fund 1898-1905 (Volume 5)
- Church Publications 1867-2000
  The Church Publications series (approx. 6.5 linear feet) spans the dates 1867-2000, and contains Cathedral Digest, The Calendar of St. Paul's Cathedral and St. Paul's Monthly Notice Paper. Also included in this series are bulletins from weekly services, special service calendars and catalogues, and yearbooks.
  - The Calendar of St. Paul's Cathedral, 1895-1939 (Box 8)
    (yearly bound volumes)
  - The Calendar of St. Paul's Cathedral, 1940-1961 (Box 9)
  - Cathedral bulletins
    - By date 1994-1999 (Box 10)
    - By seasons, Advent-Pentecost 1990s (with some earlier) (Box 11)
    - Church Year readings 1990s (Box 12)
    - Special occasions 1980s-1990s (Box 12)
  - Cathedral Digest
    - 1969-1995, 10 folders; 5 volumes (Box 13)
    - 1999-2000, 1 folders (Box 13)
  - Earlier published materials
    - St. Paul's Monthly Notice Paper 1899-1905 (Box 14)
    - Sunday School Catalogues 1896-1897, 1902 (Box 14)
    - Special Calendars 1888-1950
      - Easter 1888, 1892 (Box 14)
      - Lent 1925, 1948 (Box 14)
      - Christmas 1929, 1931, 1940, 1950 (Box 14)
    - Year Books 1938-1940, 1948 (Box 14)
    - Installations and Consecration Services 1925, 1937, 1940-1943, 1947 (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous 1867-1969 (Box 14)
- Annual Reports / Annual Meeting Reports
  The Annual Reports/Annual Meeting Reports series (0.5 linear feet) is a valuable source of ready information on the activities of the church. The series dates from 1954 to 2001.
  - 1954-2001 (some gaps), 2 folders (Box 14)
- Vestry Records
  The Vestry Records (3 linear feet) series includes minutes of meetings, reports, mailings, and other materials relating to the operation of the church. The series dates from 1964 to 1995.
  - Yearly files 1964-1986 (Box 15)
  - Yearly files 1987-1995 (Box 16)
  - Minutes 1982-1995 (Box 17)
- Topical Files 1950-2001 (mainly 1980s-1990s)
  The Topical Files series (8 linear feet) dates from 1950 to 2001 with the bulk of the material falling within the period of the 1980s and 90s. Arranged alphabetically, the series documents the management of the Cathedral facility, the involvement of the church in the mid-city neighborhood of Detroit, especially the University Cultural Center Area.
  - Acolytes 1990-1999 (Box 18)
  - Advertising 1999-2000 (Box 18)
  - AIDS, Interfaith 1997-1999 (Box 18)
  - All Saints Vestry Overnight 1990-1992 (Box 18)
  - Alpha Seminar 1999 (Box 18)
  - Altar Guild 1994-1997 (Box 18)
  - Anglican -- Roman Catholic International Commission 1999 (Box 18)
  - Anti-Crime Conference 1994 (Box 18)
  - Apportionment 1995-2001 (Box 18)
  - Articles of Incorporation and Bylaws 1958 (Box 18)
  - Audits 1986-1993 (Box 18)
  - Bishop's Dinner 1997 (Box 18)
  - Bishop's Visitations 1994-2001 (Box 18)
  - Book Store 1971-2001 (Box 18)
  - Budget
    - 1993 (Box 18)
    - 1994 (Box 18)
  - Canadian-American Friendship Day Service 1957-1968 (Box 18)
  - Canons, Honorary 1994 (Box 18)
  - Capital Campaign Philanthropic Market Study1996-1998 (Box 18)
  - Casinos 1997-1998 (Box 18)
  - Cathedral
    - Chapter 1975-2001 (Box 18)
    - Clergy Utilization 1995 (Box 18)
    - Lighting Proposal 1991 (Box 18)
    - Plot Plan 1962 (Box 18)
    - Teleconferencing, ECTN 1993 (Box 18)
    - Tours, Self Guided 1992-1998, undated, 3 folders (Box 18)
  - Chancel/Sanctuary Basic Floor Plan undated (Box 18)
  - Chaplaincy Fundraiser 1998 (Box 18)
  - Christian Education 1984-1998 (Box 18)
  - Christian Education Committee 1994-1995 (Box 18)
  - Clerestory Window Gifts undated (Box 18)
  - Clergy Conference 1996-2000 (Box 18)
  - Clericus 1998-2000 (Box 18)
  - Coalition for Human Needs of the Episcopal Church 1991 (Box 18)
  - Columbarium 1983-1988 (Box 18)
  - Combined Episcopal Services Appeal (CESA) 1994-1997 (Box 18)
  - Committee, Cathedral Nominating (Box 18)
  - Community Economic Development (CDC) Trade Association 1998 (Box 18)
  - Community Foundation for Southeastern Michigan 1987-1993, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Communications Guild 1980-1986 (Box 19)
  - Community Service Awards Dinner 1992 (Box 19)
  - Computer Committee 1996-1999 (Box 19)
  - Concordat
    - Episcopal & Lutheran 1994-1997 (Box 19)
    - St. Paul's & Diocese 1995 (Box 19)
  - Congregations Survey, Detroit Area 1997 (Box 19)
  - Connections 1997 (Box 19)
  - Convention 1999 (Box 19)
  - Constitutions and Canons 1996 (Box 19)
  - Correspondence
    - 1982 (Box 19)
    - 1984 (Box 19)
    - 1985 (Box 19)
    - 1987 (Box 19)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 19)
  - Crossroads
    - By-Laws, Minutes, Financial
      - 1979-1983 (Box 20)
      - 1984-1986 (Box 20)
      - 1991 (Box 20)
      - 1992-1994 (Box 20)
      - 1995-1999 (Box 20)
      - 2000-2001 (Box 20)
    - Grants & Loans 1983 (Box 20)
    - Joint Crossroads Board/Cathedral Vestry 1984 (Box 20)
    - Options & Deeds 1982-1983 (Box 20)
  - Deacons 1998 (Box 20)
  - Dean Search 1978-1979 (Box 20)
  - Deanery 1979-1980 (Box 20)
  - Detroit Board of Education 1996 (Box 20)
  - Detroit Development Improvement 1998 (Box 20)
  - Detroit Historic Churches Association 1988-2000 (Box 20)
  - Detroit Neighborhood and Family Initiative (NFI)
    - Back to Basics 1998-1999 (Box 20)
    - Bylaws undated (Box 20)
    - CEED 1999 (Box 20)
    - Development Committee 1999-2000 (Box 20)
    - Economic Development 1998-1999 (Box 20)
    - Memos
      - 1997-1999 (Box 20)
      - 1999-2000 (Box 20)
    - New Beginnings 2001 (Box 20)
    - Seedco 1997-2000 (Box 20)
  - Detroit Strategic Planning Project 1987 (Box 20)
  - Development Committee
    - 1986-1990 (Box 20)
    - 1991-1994 (Box 20)
  - Diocese Convention to Elect Co-Adjutor May 1988 (Box 20)
  - Diocesan Trustees 1997-2000 (Box 20)
  - Disabilities, Task Force on Ministry to and with People with 1988-1989 (Box 20)
  - Eastside Area Council 1995-2000 (Box 21)
  - Economic Justice, McGehee Fund 1991-2001 (Box 21)
  - Environmental Diversified Services 1990 (Box 21)
  - Episcopal Church Women 1977-1998 (Box 21)
  - Episcopal Election, Michigan 1988 (Box 21)
  - Episcopal Growth and Income Fund 1996 (Box 21)
  - Episcopal Medical Missions Foundation 1995-2000 (Box 21)
  - Family Assistance & Service Trust 1985-1986 (Box 21)
  - Financial Stewardship Committee 1985 (Box 21)
  - Garfield Building 1990-1993 (Box 21)
  - Gay-Lesbian 1996 (Box 21)
  - General Convention
    - 1981-1982 (Box 21)
    - 1991 (Box 21)
    - Miscellaneous 1982-1988 (Box 21)
  - Gibbs, Wendell N. 1999 (Box 21)
  - Global Episcopal Mission, GEM 1997 (Box 21)
  - Goals 1994 (Box 21)
  - Greater Downtown Partnership, Inc. 1997-1998 (Box 21)
  - Grubbs, Dale 1990 (Box 21)
  - Healing Mission 1996 (Box 21)
  - Herlong, Bertram, Sermons
    - 1980-1984 (Box 21)
    - 1985-1987 (Box 21)
    - 1988-1993 (Box 21)
  - Historical Courtyards and Gardens 1997-2000 (Box 21)
  - Historical Data, Cathedral (Box 21)
  - Historical Marker 1979-1992 (Box 21)
  - Historical Society 1980-1981 (Box 21)
  - Homeless, Services to 2000 (Box 21)
  - Hospitality 1997-1998 (Box 21)
  - Investment Committee
    - 1985 (Box 22)
    - 1987-1993 (Box 22)
  - Jewish Vocational Services Building 1992 (Box 22)
  - Lawsuits 1984-1988 (Box 22)
  - Lay Ministries Commissioning undated (Box 22)
  - Lay Persons 1988-1991 (Box 22)
  - Lay Readers 1989-1998 (Box 22)
  - Leave a Legacy 1997-2000 (Box 22)
  - Lent
    - 1986-1991 (Box 22)
    - 1992-1995 (Box 22)
    - 1996 (Box 22)
    - 1997 (Box 22)
    - 1998 (Box 22)
  - Lighting
    - 1971 (Box 22)
    - 1996-2002 (Box 22)
  - Liturgy Committee
    - 1990-1994 (Box 22)
    - 1997 (Box 22)
  - Loans & Grants Committee 1981-1992 (Box 22)
  - Long Range Planning Committee
    - 1980, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - 1981-1986 (Box 22)
    - 1989 (Box 22)
    - 1990 (Box 22)
    - 1991 (Box 22)
    - 1992-1998 (Box 22)
  - Marriage Canons 1982 (Box 23)
  - Mayson Memorial 1995-2002 (Box 23)
  - Memorial Garden 1997-1998 (Box 23)
  - Memorials
    - MLK 1996-2000 (Box 23)
    - Rea 1950-1963 (Box 23)
    - Walker, John T. 1994 (Box 23)
    - Warren, Dean L. G. 1983 (Box 23)
  - Metamorphosis 1998 (Box 23)
  - Metropolitan Christian Council: Detroit-Windsor 2000 (Box 23)
  - Michigan Cancer 1994 (Box 23)
  - Mid City Concerned Citizens District Council
    - By-Laws & Articles of Incorporation 1988 (Box 23)
    - General
      - Undated (Box 23)
      - 1980-1982 (Box 23)
      - 1983 (Box 23)
      - 1984 (Box 23)
      - 1987-1988 (Box 23)
      - 1989 (Box 23)
      - 1990 (Box 23)
      - 1991 (Box 23)
      - 1992 (Box 23)
      - 1994 (Box 23)
  - Ministry of Money
    - 1988 (Box 23)
    - 1989 (Box 23)
  - Mission Committee 1981-1992 (Box 23)
  - Mission Statement 1997 (Box 23)
  - Music 1984-1988 (Box 23)
  - New Clergy Support 1997-1998 (Box 23)
  - New Member Welcome Letters 1991 (Box 23)
  - Noel Night 1982-2000 (Box 23)
  - Office for the Blessing of: Dean's House, Associate Rector's House undated (Box 23)
  - Orchestra Place Development Corporation 1981-1986 (Box 23)
  - Ordained Ministry 1993 (Box 23)
  - Organ 1989-1999 (Box 23)
  - Parish Meetings-Special 1996-1997 (Box 24)
  - Passions undated (Box 24)
  - Pastoral Associates/Lay Ministry Service, P.A.L.M.S.
    - General 1980-1982, 2 folders (Box 24)
    - Demonstration Project Proposal 1979-1981 (Box 24)
  - Pastoral Care Committee 1994-1998 (Box 24)
  - Pastoral Committee 1980-1992 (Box 24)
  - Pavilion Ground Breaking, G.M. and N.W. 1984 (Box 24)
  - People United as One 1997 (Box 24)
  - Petition, Re: Brunson 1989 (Box 24)
  - Philadelphia Office of the Episcopal Church 1990-1991 (Box 24)
  - Photographs undated (Box 24)
  - Planned Giving 1985-1993 (Box 24)
  - Preaching Mission 1997-1999, 3 folders (Box 24)
  - Project Compassion 1997-1998 (Box 24)
  - Property Committee 1989-1992 (Box 24)
  - Race Reconciliation 1996-1998 (Box 24)
  - Radio Program/Clinton R. Andrews 1979-1986 (Box 24)
  - Regional Confirmation 1993 (Box 24)
  - St. Luke's Day 1987-1991 (Box 24)
  - St. Martha's 1996-1997 (Box 24)
  - St. Matthew Passion 1980 (Box 24)
  - School of Theology 1989 (Box 24)
  - School of Theology, Board of Advisors 1980-1983 (Box 24)
  - Sexual Misconduct Policies Etc. 1993-1994 (Box 24)
  - South American Missionary Society (SAMS) 1996-1997 (Box 24)
  - Special Services 1994-1995 (Box 24)
  - Stewardship/Commitment 1989-1994 (Box 24)
  - Tower 1981-1982 (Box 24)
  - United Thank Offering (UTO) 1992-2001 (Box 24)
  - University Cultural Center Area (UCCA)
    - General
      - 1987 (Box 24)
      - 1988-1994 (Box 24)
      - 1995-1997 (Box 24)
      - 1998 (Box 24)
      - 1999-2000 (Box 24)
    - Apartment/Condominium Overview 1991 (Box 24)
    - Development Committee 1987-1991 (Box 24)
    - Ex-Committee 1988-1990 (Box 25)
    - Festival of the Arts
      - 1987 (Box 25)
      - 1988 (Box 25)
      - 1999-2000 (Box 25)
  - Ushers 1976 (Box 25)
  - Venture in Mission 1980-1981 (Box 25)
  - Vestry
    - By-Laws, Conference 1991-1995 (Box 25)
    - Candidates 1981-1982 (Box 25)
    - General
      - 1991 (Box 25)
      - 1992 (Box 25)
      - 1993 (Box 25)
      - 1994 (Box 25)
      - 1997-1999 (Box 25)
      - 2000 (Box 25)
    - Rosters 1974-1993 (Box 25)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 25)
  - Violence Prevention Task Force 1998 (Box 25)
  - Vision Statement 1996-1999 (Box 25)
  - Volunteers 1995 (Box 25)
  - Weaver, John 1981-1996 (Box 25)
  - Whitaker School of Theology
    - 1994-1995 (Box 25)
    - 1996-2001 (Box 25)
  - Women in Ministry 1994 (Box 25)
  - Woodward Corridor 1989-2000 (Box 25)
  - Woodward Heritage Route 1997-1998 (Box 25)
  - Woodward-Mid City Feasibility Study 1992 (Box 25)
  - Woodward Parking 1995-1996 (Box 25)
  - Worship Guidelines, Epis/ELCA 2000-2001 (Box 25)
  - Youth 1996-2000 (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous 1989-1995 (Box 25)
- Miscellaneous earlier records 1851-1943
  The Miscellaneous Earlier Records series (approx. 0.25 linear feet and 4 oversize volumes) spans the dates 1851-1943, and contains letters of transfer, newspaper clippings, and parochial records. Also included in this series is the score from "Pilgrimage, a parable with music" (2 vols.), and a set of scrapbooks (2 vols.).
  - Letters of Transfer 1938-1940 (Box 25)
  - Boundary Case 1851 (Box 25)
  - Parochial Reports 1917-1920 (Box 25)
  - Newspaper Clippings undated (Box 25)
  - "Pilgrimage, a parable with music"
    - Act I (Volume 1)
    - Act II (Volume 2)
  - Scrapbooks
    - January-November 1936 (Volume 3)
    - January 1940-July 1943 (Volume 4)
Related Material
The library also has a collection of The Cathedral News dated from 1948 to 1969. This newsletter is stored separated from the records of the Cathedral.